<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The deputies of the Republick of Amsterdam to the States of Holland convicted of high-treason written and proved by the Minister of State, according to a true copy printed at the Hague, 1684.</title>
            <author>Philalethes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12952570</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12952570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95994</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95994)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 735:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The deputies of the Republick of Amsterdam to the States of Holland convicted of high-treason written and proved by the Minister of State, according to a true copy printed at the Hague, 1684.</title>
                  <author>Philalethes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>55 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 48: Philalethes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>United Provinces of the Netherlands. --  Staten Generaal.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95994:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DEPUTIES Of the REPUBLICK of AMSTERDAM TO THE States of Holland Convicted of <hi>High-Treaſon,</hi> Written and Proved By the Miniſter of State.</p>
            <p>According to a true Copy Printed at the <hi>HAG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> 1684.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_States_of_Holland">
            <pb facs="tcp:95994:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95994:2"/>
            <head>The DEPUTIES of the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick of <hi>AMSTERDAM</hi> to the States of <hi>HOLLAND</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of High-Treaſon.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas you deſire to be inform'd of me in ſome meaſure of what paſſed in the Aſſembly of the Lords the States on the 16th of <hi>Feb.</hi> laſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which in this our Countrey ſo much noiſe has been made, and whereof the Lords the Burgomaſters and Regents of the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſo much complain; I do preſume to think my ſelf able to give you, and all that think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves concerned in the true repreſentation of that affair, the following information, whereof all thoſe will be able to judge who for any time ſince have been preſent at the ſaid Aſſembly; which is this.</p>
            <p>The Marquiſs <hi>de Grana</hi> having ſent to his Highneſs the P. of <hi>Orange</hi> a Letter written by the Count <hi>D'avaux,</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Ambaſſadour from the K. of <hi>France</hi> to this State, on the 19th of <hi>January</hi> laſt to the King his Maſter,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95994:3"/>
part in Cifer and part in plain writing, with a Copy of what was cifered, and beſides 3 other Letters; which Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſaid Count <hi>D'avaux</hi> with the extracts of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid 3 particular Letters as much as concerned publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs are already Printed and made publick: His Highneſs conſidered for ſome days what he ſhould doe with the ſaid Letters, for that the matter therein contained was of great importance, and that the State was much concerned to be informed of the correſpondence therein mentioned, and that therefore they ought not to be kept ſecret, the more for that ſome time ſince, and eſpecially about the time of the writing of the ſaid Letter, great muttering was among the reſpective Members in the Aſſembly of the States againſt the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> concerning the correſpondence which the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that City had with foreign Miniſters without impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame to the States, and from whoſe communication the ſaid deputed Lords uſed many diſcourſes in the Aſſembly of the ſaid States, which upon enquiry were found falſe. His Highneſs thought it therefore beſt at firſt not to concern Juſtice therewith but immediately to acquaint the Lords therewith, and to leave it to their wiſedoms to act therein, that it might not be ſaid that his Highneſs had either done therein too much or too little (as he notwithſtanding all his faithfulneſs and moderation ſhewed on all occaſions, but chiefly when the Government was almoſt in the uttermoſt confuſion, was charged with many forged calumnies chiefly in the ſaid City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi>) and accordingly on the 16th of this preſent Month, being preſent at the meeting of their Lordſhips, he acquainted them that he had ſomewhat to communicate to them of the higheſt importance, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the Members of that Aſſembly would appoint that the Doors of their Meeting place might be ſhut; <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe of going out of the houſe, that ſo by the going out and in of any of their Members the matter might not be divulged;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95994:3"/>
that any one deſiring might be admitted in, but that none ſhould be ſuffered to go forth without leave of their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; whereupon none of the Members replying or moving ought to conſideration, the Lord Penſioner of <hi>Holland</hi> rung the Bell to call in one of the Door-keepers, and told him, It was the order of the Lords the States that he ſhould ſhut the Doors of their Aſſembly place and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing chambers thereto adjoyning, and admit entrance to any deſiring it, but to let none out without order of their Lordſhips, none of the Members of the Aſſembly contradicting the order, or moving ought to the contrary. Then his Highneſs proceeded ſaying, that what he had to communicate concerned in ſome manner as therein nam'd the perſons of the Lords <hi>Hooft, Hop,</hi> old <hi>Schepens,</hi> and Councellor and Penſionary of the City of <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> wherefore his Highneſs deſired that the ſaid Lords would retire into the withdrawing room of the States, whereupon the ſaid Penſioner <hi>Hop</hi> having firſt ſpoken to the Lord of <hi>Marſſe Veen</hi> Burgomaſter of the ſaid City, and deputed by the ſaid City to the Aſſembly; the ſaid two Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> without alledging ought to conſideration, or that ought was moved by the Lords Deputies of the ſaid City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> or of any of the other Cities, retired into the withdrawing room, whereupon his Highneſs diſcloſed the matter to the Lords the States in the Aſſembly, namely, that he had received theſe Letters and the original Letter partly in Cifer and partly in plain writing with the unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering thereof, and gave the 3 Letters into the hands of the Lord Penſioner of <hi>Holland</hi> who read the ſame, then his Highneſs declared he had now performed his duty as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, leaving the full liberty and diſpoſal thereof to their Lordſhips to act therein as they ſhould judge neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the ſervice of their Countrey. The Lords riſing from their Table to deliberate what might be the effect of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95994:4"/>
this overture, and the other Members alſo preparing to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> without order and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Aſſembly entred in again, and ſaid they ought to be preſent when they were to deliberate on the ſaid mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whereupon many Debates were occaſioned among the Members of the Aſſembly, ſome alledging they ought to abſent, and all the other Lords, except thoſe of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> deſired them at leaſt in diſcretion to abſent; whereto the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> would in no wiſe yield, ſo that the other Lords to cauſe therein no commotion, and being reſolved to give no other advice in the ſaid matter, but what they ſhould judge to conſiſt with all Juſtice and Equity and the ſervice of their Countrey, reſolved to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, although the two aforeſaid Lords were preſent, and ſo inſiſted no longer on their retirement; notwithſtanding thoſe Members who were for the retirement of the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop,</hi> expreſly declared that according to the cuſtome of all ſuch Aſſemblies, and eſpecially accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the moſt ancient cuſtome and reſolution of their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, the retirement of the ſaid <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> ought not to be left to their diſcretion, but that they ought to be regulated by the foreſaid reſolution and cuſtome; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the other Members having proceeded to give their ſentiments, they all concluded to give knowledge of this diſcovery to the Lords the Burgomaſters and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>council their principals and that all the Papers which were in the Cloſets of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> or in the Chamber of the ſaid Lord Penſioner <hi>Hop</hi> ſhould by ſome of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thereto deputed, be ſealed up and left in the cuſtody of the ſaid Lord of <hi>Marſſe Veen,</hi> and the ſealing of them up ſhould be done by the Lords <hi>Vander Gaes,</hi> and <hi>Boert</hi> Burgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter and Penſioner reſpective of the Cities of <hi>Delft</hi> and <hi>Alkmar</hi> and the Lord Secretary <hi>Van Beamant,</hi> and that to the ſealing thereof they ſhould uſe their own particular
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95994:4"/>
ſeals. And all the Members and particularly alſo the Lords deputed of the ſaid City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> undertook to give cognizance of the diſcovery and Letters to their Principals the Burgomaſters and Common-council of their ſaid Cities, but of the ſealing up thoſe Papers onely to the Lords Burgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters all under the ſame Oath of Secreſie; excepting that the Lords deputed of the City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> ſince this Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of theſe Papers chiefly concerned them, ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the ſame alſo to their Common council, ſo that nothing elſe was debated in the ſaid Aſſembly, but what concerned the diſcovery made by his Highneſs, and the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or preſence of the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> during the Debate on the ſaid diſcovery, the ſealing and ſecuring their Papers, and the ſaid reſolution of Secreſie.</p>
            <p>I leave it to your wiſe and ſerious judgment if any who is but any thing impartial could or ought to have otherwiſe managed an affair of ſo great importance and of ſo fair a proſpect as the contents of the ſaid Letters, and if any thing hath been amiſs, it might in truth be ſaid to have been rather by too great moderation than rigour.</p>
            <p>But whether or no the Lords the Burgomaſters and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-council of the City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> whoſe Deputies had undertaken to keep the matter ſecret and not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the ſame unto their ſaid Burgomaſters and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>council, but under a like Oath of Secreſie have regulated themſelves according to thoſe promiſes when they by their Letters communicated the ſame to the Burgomaſters and Governours of the other Cities, and permitted, atleaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived the publiſhing the ſame by their City Printer.</p>
            <p>But that I may give the better information herein, It will be needfull to conſider what it properly is that the Lords the Burgomaſters and Governours of the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> complain of in relation to that Letter; and that is, Firſt concerning the ſhutting of the Doors, Secondly, concerning
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95994:5"/>
the withdrawing of the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop,</hi> and Thirdly concerning the ſealing up of their Papers. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the firſt it is ſufficiently known to be the cuſtome, that when their Lordſhips in their Aſſembly have been in debate concerning a matter of great import, that they have cauſed the doors of their Aſſembly place to be ſhut, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the going forth of any without knowledge of their Lordſhips; the examples of which are ſo known, that all thoſe who have frequented that Aſſembly for ſome years ſince cannot be ignorant of, ſo that the ſaid Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moncouncil have no cauſe to complain thereof as a matter extraordinary and unheard of; and that the Penſionary Councellor of <hi>Holland</hi> ſhould alone have given order con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame, without firſt putting the queſtion round to all the Members of the Aſſembly, is wrongly mentioned; for his Highneſs had openly deſired it of all the Members preſent, that for the importance of the buſineſs, and for that many of the Members did often uſe to go out and come in, that therefore the doors of the ſaid place might be ſhut; and that no man contradicted that matter, or urged any the leaſt conſideration againſt the ſo doing. It was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the place of the Lord Penſionary Councellor to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie unto thoſe who in the Aſſembly are concerned, the pleaſure of the Lords the States, and accordingly the Door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers being called in, he told them the reſolution of the States to have the doors ſhut, which he did not privately but in the hearing of the whole Aſſembly, without oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, contradiction or appearance thereof by any; and ſince I cannot perceive wherein he the ſaid Lord Penſionary Councellor hath done ill or againſt the orders of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, notwithſtanding that period might eaſily admit ſuch an interpretation, as if he had deſigned to himſelf an unjuſt and illegal power; I muſt therefore believe that the ſame is rather pretended out of animoſity than reaſon, the rather
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95994:5"/>
for that in the ſame Letter it is inſinuated by a repetition to have been the ſole duty of the Lord Penſionary Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, eſpecially when you ſhall pleaſe to call to mind that in matters of much greater import than is that of ſhutting and opening the Doors of the Aſſembly place, the ſaid Councellor Penſionary hath been uſed oftentimes to take the reſolution of the Aſſembly as concluded, without moving the queſtion round to every particular Member, when none of the Members have objected any thing againſt what was moved. As to the ſecond point concerning the preſence or abſence of the Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> during the opening and debate on the aforeſaid Letter, I deſire you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that it is not onely uſed in all Collegiate Aſſemblies that thoſe on whoſe matters the debate is, when they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame Aſſembly, ſhould abſent themſelves during the ſaid Debate, to leave unto the reſt a freedom in debate of the ſaid matter, to give their ſentiments free and undiſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; and that alſo the inſtructions of moſt Collegiate Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies are to that end directed, and that it hath alſo been a very ancient cuſtome in the aſſembly of the Lords the States that not onely thoſe in whoſe matters particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and reſolutions are to be had, are to abſent themſelves from that Aſſembly, but that alſo the abſence hath been commanded of thoſe that were their nigheſt relations, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their quality in that preſent Aſſembly; yea that even the Lords deputed to that Aſſembly by the ſingle notice given by the then Lord Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> are accuſtomed to abſent when in the Aſſembly any debates were to be had concerning the Cities from whence they were deputed; yea alſo in ſuch an occaſion when all the members of the ſaid Aſſembly having on the matter in debate brought in the advice of the Lords their Principals, and ſhould adviſe not according to their own judgment as on accidental cauſes, but even when they alone
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95994:6"/>
are to deliver the charge of the Lords their Principals in which the preſence of ſuch Members could make no change, yea, that the deputed Lords of ſuch Cities deſiring not to be abſent out of the Aſſembly that they might onely hear the Lords Principals of the other Members; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they have been neceſſitated to obey the orders given them to abſent, although it were but by the plurality of the Votes of the other Members, and that ſeveral of the other Members declared themſelves free to utter their minds in preſence of thoſe Members which were ordered to abſent. The Aſſembly of their Lordſhips have judged it neceſſary in matters of the leaſt importance, and therefore as an expreſs reſolution have cauſed it to be regiſtred, <hi>viz.</hi> that each one concerning whom as to the diſtribution of any Office or place, it was deliberated, that during that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration he ſhould be abſent, to leave them free to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation. It is true that the Lord <hi>Marſveen</hi> Burgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of the ſaid City and deputed to the Aſſembly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted to be ignorant of all the correſpondencies mentioned in that Letter; and that the Lord old Burgomaſter <hi>Van Opmeer</hi> had ſaid that the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> had done nothing without order, but 'tis alſo true that that Order could not qualifie the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſaid deliberation to be preſent in the Aſſembly, ſince by reaſon and very ancient cuſtome in ſuch a caſe all thoſe who had participated in the ſame matter, yea alſo all the Lords deputed of that City ought to have abſented themſelves if the Lords the Members of the Aſſembly had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted thereon.</p>
            <p>But it is ſaid the Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> were not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly named in the ſaid Letter of the Count <hi>D'Avaux,</hi> none but the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> being therein expreſſed, and when the Lord Councellor Penſionary ſaid to them that on the day of the writing of the ſaid Letter they had been at the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95994:6"/>
houſe of the ſaid Embaſſadour, they proved they were then elſewhere. It were in truth to be wiſhed, that when they would make known matters of that nature to Members of the Government for their diſcharge, they ſhould then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the truth thereof without any colouring; it is true that the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> are not mentioned in the ſaid Letter by name, and that therein is onely expreſt <hi>Meſſieurs D'Amſterdam</hi> the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> but it is alſo true that what in the Letter of the ſaid Embaſſadour is mentioned muſt have been tranſacted by theſe Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> who had ſpoke with the ſaid Lord Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of <hi>France;</hi> ſince thoſe who had not ſpoken with the ſaid Embaſſadour, by the name of <hi>Meſſieurs d'Amſterdam,</hi> the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> who had told him thus, as is expreſs'd in the Letter, could not be comprehended. Now it is true and acknowledged as well by the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> as by the Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop,</hi> that the ſame Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> were the ſame who had ſpoken with the Lord Embaſſadour, and I know none that ſhall juſtly judge, but will find a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference therein, whether the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour in the aforeſaid Letter ſhould have named the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop,</hi> or that he ſhould ſay the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> had told me thus, when it muſt be conſtrued from the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the ſaid Lords, that the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> were the ſame who at that time were with him and ſpoke with him without being able to name any others, and although it be true that the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> when the Lord Penſionary Councellor asked them if on the Sunday when the Letter was written they had not been at his houſe, they anſwered in the Negative, and could prove themſelves to have been elſewhere; but it is alſo true the ſaid Lord Penſionary was miſtaken in the day, and that the ſaid Lords acknowledged to have been the day before, namely, Saturday, with the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95994:7"/>
ſpoke to him as he expreſly hath mentioned it in the ſaid Letter, and I leave it to your judgment whether in this they proceeded with the required ſincerity when they carp at the miſ-expreſſion of the day, when the truth of their ſpeaking to the Embaſſadour and the time thereof and their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion may conſiſt together. When now the reſolution of the Lords the States and the practice thereon ſucceeding expreſly infer that thoſe whoſe affair was in deliberation before the Aſſembly ought to abſent during thoſe delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that by the confeſſion as well of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> as of the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> it appeareth that they are the ſame who had ſpoke with the ſaid Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and that it is therefore their caſe that is in debate; and that the ſaid Lords took the power to be preſent notwithſtanding many of the Members were of judgment that they ſhould conform to the aforeſaid reſolution and practice; and I judge that all impartial men will adjudge that act of theirs in thus ſtaying in the Aſſembly a very great diſreſpect ſhewed to their Sovereign Power there lawfully aſſembled, and informing themſelves and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating concerning actions not onely in themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, but alſo in the higheſt puniſhable, and ſaid by them to have been acted. And that the other Members of their Lordſhips aſſembly had great reaſon to complain of them and to reſent the wrong done them by the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> depending on their own authority as if they were not tied to the foreſaid reſolutions nor any practice enſuing thereon.</p>
            <p>Concerning the third point, to wit the ſealing up of the aforeſaid Papers, the aforeſaid Lords Burgomaſters and Common-council of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have as little reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain as they have concerning the ſhutting of the doors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned; or the required abſence of the Lords. <hi>Hooft</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95994:7"/>
and <hi>Hop,</hi> but that this may the better appear we muſt of neceſſity touch ſomewhat nearer the matter giving occaſion to that reſolution of theirs for Sealing up the foreſaid Papers, which was this; that their Lordſhips perceived out of the forementioned Letter of the ſaid Embaſſadour that what was written was not to a private friend to whom a man might write his ſentiment as he pleaſed, but that it was writ to the King his Maſter to whom he was obliged to give an exact account of all his negotiations, and whom he ought not nor could abuſe, and writ to him of ſeveral matters, concerning which he ſaid to have treated with the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and that he judged them of ſuch importance that to the end the King his Maſter might alſo be informed thereof, he ſent that Letter with an expreſs Poſt by one of his own dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks; ſo that what is charged on the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> was not founded on a ſuppoſition or on the ſaying of a third perſon, but on the Letter of an Embaſſadour writ to his King, to whom he is obliged to give an account of all his Negotiations, and not of that which was related to him by a third perſon, or what he learned accidentally, but of ſomething that himſelf in perſon had treated with the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> alſo in perſon, and whereon he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected farther order in anſwer from the ſaid King his Maſter. I need not, Sir, acquaint you with the duty of an Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour as well known unto your ſelf as to any other, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Character given them which they may make uſe of, in not dealing too ſtrictly juſt with thoſe to whom they are ſent, they are not by common reaſon therefore diſpenſed from giving to their Principals an exact true and faithfull account to the utmoſt of their power, of all their tranſactions and intelligence gained, eſpecially in the moſt eſſential parts thereof. And therefore that the Count <hi>D'Avaux</hi> who hath ſo many years performed the function of an Embaſſadour, and that with ſo general approbation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95994:8"/>
of all men, who if I may ſo ſay hath been educated under the tuition of the late Count <hi>D'Avaux,</hi> who hath gained the repute throughout the World to have been one of the greateſt Maſters in matters of Negotiations and Treaties, and who fully underſtood the duty of an Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour as is manifeſt by the Negotiations he hath treated. That he could fail in one of the moſt eſſential duties of an Embaſſadour, <hi>viz.</hi> the giving of a true and exact account to the King his Maſter of that which himſelf had treated about, and that therein he would abuſe him, even ſuch a King who ſo well knoweth to make himſelf obeyed by thoſe that ſerve him, or to puniſh the leaſt failure therein, will by none be conſented to who is not prejudiced. And this is alſo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in confirmed, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had with the ſame Lord Embaſſadour ſuch a familiar converſe, that the other Members of the Aſſembly were ever therewith offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and that the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> were admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to quit or moderate that ſo offending communication by the other Members before the Aſſembly was met and ready to deliberate; and when ſeveral of the Members ſtood diſcourſing together, and at the end of their debates had quitted their places, even then the Lord Councellor Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Hop</hi> with a great confidence, and to a farther diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of very many Members, anſwered, that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood their liberty to go ſo often to the Lord Embaſſadour as they ſhould think fit; yea, and that with ſo much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confidence he expreſt himſelf, that the ſaid Lords depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had inſerted ſome things in their advices, which the Miniſter of the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> ſhould have ſaid; and his Highneſs being informed by the ſaid Miniſter of <hi>England,</hi> that what was alledged was untruth, and having thereof given notice to the Aſſembly of the Lords the States, with complaint concerning the conduct of thoſe of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> At the ſame time, and on the deliberation for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95994:8"/>
a farther prohibition of communication with Foreign Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters concerning affairs of the State, The ſaid Lords Deputies in the Aſſembly in their turn expreſſing their ſenſe by the mouth of the ſaid Lord Penſionary <hi>Hop,</hi> in a braving manner declared they were reſolved not to ceaſe that communication, and that they would yet that After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon ſpeak with the Lord Embaſſadour of <hi>France,</hi> that the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour gave them thereto encouragement, that he had ſpoke to them on <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Eve of ſome matters concerning the Trade for St. <hi>Vallery,</hi> and that on occaſion of theſe particular matters he ſometimes intermingled ſome State Affairs, but that thereof they had given an account to the Lords their Principals, that they alſo had been at <hi>Delft</hi> to confer with them, that they were convinced of their endeavours to the welfare of the Republick, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were not obliged to reflect on the jealouſie of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; but not in all this touching one word concerning the matters relating to the Commonwealth, whereof was treated between them and the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour; and that the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> farther acknowledged that the ſaid Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> had been with the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour the day before the writing of that Letter; add thereto that ſeveral matters mentioned in the ſame Letter that the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhould have done, were alſo in truth by them effected, as I ſhall hereafter more at large demonſtrate, and that ſo many circumſtances concurred with the ſaid fact as ſeldom can be brought together to make clearly out the truth of a matter treated of between a few perſons. What the contents of the ſaid Letter were, you may collect out of the Printed Letter of the Count <hi>D'Avaux,</hi> and I would not have made farther mention thereof if I had not thought it needfull for your better information to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the contents thereof ſomewhat more particularly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95994:9"/>Sir, you may remember with what immoderate zeal the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have endeavoured to oblige the other Members under pretext of Counſel to force the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to accept of one of the Equivalents expreſſed in the memorial of the Count <hi>D'Avaux</hi> of the Fifth of <hi>November</hi> laſt, you will poſſibly alſo know at leaſt many Lords who frequent the Aſſemblies of the Lords the States, have at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times heard that when the poor Inhabitants of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> were bewailed, and that men even ſtood amazed at the deſolations which the hard, Unchriſtian, yea Inhumane procedures of the <hi>French</hi> effected; that it hath often been ſaid by ſome of thoſe Lords, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> muſt be thereby forced to give ſatisfaction to the King of <hi>France;</hi> that it was a puniſhment which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> muſt ſuffer for not reſolving to comply with the will of the King of <hi>France,</hi> and many other like diſcourſes you may remember, alſo how oft they have deſired that Debates ſhould be had on the ſaid memorial of the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> how often they have obliged the Members to confer with their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals concerning the ſame after they had already by formal reſolutions in their Councils taken ſeveral times declared that <hi>Spain</hi> muſt accept one of the Equivalents, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could no more confer with their Fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers on the ſame ſubject; what particular endeavours the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have uſed now with the one, then with the other Member, yea ſo much that the other Members have been offended thereat, with what earneſtneſs they have oppoſed the Levy of the Sixteen thouſand Men, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the other Members of their Lordſhips Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly conſented thereto, and which they judged ſo highly neceſſary for defence of this State, and that without it this State even without any conſideration of aſſiſtence to <hi>Spain</hi> was expoſed to the greateſt danger, and when they here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in effected nothing, they then addreſſed themſelves to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95994:9"/>
Lords deputed in the Generality from the other Provinces, and particularly alſo to the Lords deputed from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Frieſland</hi> and the Cities and Countries. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents then of the Letter is, firſt, that the Lords of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had complained to him the Lord Embaſſadour that by their ſingle Authority they could not effect that the States might deliberate on the meaſures which they had to take in caſe <hi>Spain</hi> before the end of <hi>January</hi> concluded not an accommodation with <hi>France,</hi> that he the Lord Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour could preſent no Memorial concerning the ſame, and by that means bring the matter to be deliberated not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their earneſt deſire of him to that method; they had together conſidered of all the expedients which might ſupply the effect of Memorial; that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had thereupon propoſed to him, that he would permit them, that by their means a conference might be had with him by ſome deputed out of the States General, and that in that conference a friend of the City of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> who was one of the Deputies of <hi>Holland,</hi> ſhould deſire of the Lord Embaſſadour an explanation of what might happen, if before the end of <hi>January Spain</hi> did not accept one of the Propoſals made by <hi>France,</hi> upon which he would find ſufficient matter to bring it to a deliberation among the States General; to which he had conſented; that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately thereon thoſe Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had ſpoken with ſome of the Lords deputed to the Generality, moſt of his Highneſs's party, to have a conference concerning the taking of the Ship <hi>La Regle</hi> (otherwiſe named the <hi>Terms</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> which the <hi>French</hi> had taken before the Road of <hi>Alicant</hi> from under the protection of the Flag of this State, under pretence that it was an <hi>Algerine</hi> Ship) That thoſe deputed Lords were glad to hear the complaints of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> againſt <hi>France,</hi> but there were others more fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing wherein that expedient failed them; it was truth,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95994:10"/>
and the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have been neceſſitated to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, that among others they had ſpoken with one Lord deputed to the Generality from the Province of <hi>Guelderland</hi> to bring that conference about, and it is alſo true that endeavours have been uſed for ſuch a conference, and that the holding of that conference hath been declined, not that it was ſuſpected; for as yet there was no ſuch ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> but onely for that they did not yet know wherefore a complaint ſhould be made to the Lord Embaſſadour, ſince the remedy on the complaint was to be ſought not here but in <hi>France;</hi> and that in <hi>France</hi> we had an Embaſſadour who might there move the ſaid complaints and proſecute the ſame remedy, ſo that that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treague which the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour in the foreſaid Letter ſaid, that the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had continued with him to bring the States General to deliberate concerning the aforeſaid meaſures, was in truth a buſineſs contrived by the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and which they alſo confeſſed and avowed.</p>
            <p>The Second matter contained in the Letter was, that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid firſt expedient failing, the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> would make uſe of another means, which by their vigilance ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in place of the firſt, which was on occaſion of a complement of congratulation which the Lords the States General had to make unto him the Lord Embaſſadour on the Birth of the Lord Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and that they the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had informed the Lords deputed from the Province of <hi>Frieſland</hi> City and Countrey of the whole matter, and had obliged the ſaid Lords to ſpeak to him on the ſame manner as the deputed from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhould have ſpoken to him if the deputation had been compleat. The Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> alſo muſt acknowledge that they had given notice of the deſign to the Deputies of the Province of <hi>Frieſland</hi> City and Countrey, <hi>viz.</hi> under pretence of that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95994:10"/>
conference to ſpeak of the foreſaid meaſures they were to take in caſe <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould decline the acceptance of any of the Equivalents before the end of <hi>January.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot alſo conceal from you that I ſuppoſe my ſelf to be ſufficiently informed that the day before the ſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of congratulation was to have been made, ſome Members of <hi>Holland</hi> came to the Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Holland,</hi> and asked him if the Lords appointed to perform that complement ſhould propoſe any other matters than the ſaid complement, ſaying, that they were informed, that under pretence thereof they were to ſpeak of other matters.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo true what the ſaid Letter alſo mentioneth, that after the performance of that complement there was ſpoken alſo concerning the taking the aforeſaid meaſures, and what further is mentioned concerning the ſame in the foreſaid Letter, excepting onely that in the Letter is contained that the Lords the Deputies of <hi>Frieſland</hi> City and Countrey did firſt begin the diſcourſe concerning the taking the foreſaid meaſures, and that the deputed Lords who made that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement ſay, that the diſcourſe was firſt mentioned by the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour of <hi>France,</hi> and that after they were all riſen in order to depart.</p>
            <p>In the foreſaid Letter it followeth that the Lords of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> about an hour after came to ſpeak with the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour, informing him of the endeavours which by them had been uſed; as alſo that in the Generality no deliberation was had concerning any matter, concerning which no Memorial had been preſented. And the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have been neceſſitated to acknowledge that at the ſame time they had been at the houſe of the ſaid Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, and acquainted him that in the Generality there was no deliberation upon any matters not contained in a Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:95994:11"/>The ſaid Lord Embaſſadour addeth further that the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had moreover ſaid, that when a Miniſter ſpoke with Deputies, thoſe Deputies then reſolved together, whether what was ſaid to them ſhould be propoſed as a point of deliberation, and that they had the promiſe of <hi>Frieſland</hi> City and Countrey that they would be of advice, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhould be made a point of deliberation, and would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo vote with the Lord deputed from <hi>Holland</hi> in caſe thoſe in fear of his Highneſs ſhould be of another ſentiment; and that thoſe of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſaid, that notwithſtanding all precautions they durſt not aſſure themſelves that thereof would be made a point of deliberation. And, Sir, you know that the Heer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>Werckendam</hi> who had performed the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid complement of congratulation, having communicated to the Lord Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> what the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour in the ſaid conference had ſaid concerning the taking of the aforeſaid meaſures; the ſaid Heer of <hi>Werc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kendam</hi> and Lord Councellor Penſionary were of advice that what in the aforeſaid conference was moved, muſt alſo be reported in the Aſſembly of the States. And you alſo may remember that the Lord deputed from the City and Countrey, and the Lord deputed from <hi>Frieſland,</hi> which had been preſent at the ſaid conference, being then abſent from the <hi>Hague,</hi> uſed very earneſt endeavours to the end that the ſame might be made a matter of debate by the deputies of the States, and that the Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> had inſiſted that the received and confirmed cuſtome of their Highneſſes Aſſembly muſt herein alſo be obſerved, and that to that effect the Lord Embaſſadour muſt firſt preſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Memorial, that in an orderly manner it might be known what in the aforeſaid Conference hapned, and what the true meaning was of the King of <hi>France,</hi> from which thoſe deputed Lords who aſſiſted at that Conference ſomewhat differed. It was alſo in the end reſolved, that the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95994:11"/>
ſhould be informed that in caſe he judged it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thereon to take a reſolution, that he would then without difficulty preſent the foreſaid Memorial, ſo that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the ſaid Letter in that matter agreed evidently with the truth.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Embaſſadour writeth further, that the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had ſaid that they deſired the preſentation of that Memorial, not ſo much for to have a deliberation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Generality as to make appear the good intention of his Maſter for this State, and that the knowledge they had thereof had already wrought conſiderable effects, and that they hoped yet more thereof when that ſhould be ſpread abroad.</p>
            <p>That they had alledged to him, that not to expreſs the matter too plain, and that it might appear that that propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was made to no other end, but to the advantage of the <hi>States General,</hi> that ſome allays might be found; as that he the Lord Embaſſadour had obſerved from ſeveral of the Members of State the fear they had of his Majeſties Arms, if <hi>Spain</hi> aſſented not before the end of <hi>January,</hi> that therefore his Majeſty had ordered him the ſaid Lord Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to make known to their Highneſſes, that if they remained in the State wherein they were, and hindred that the Troups they had ſent the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould not further act than in defence of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> places; his Majeſty to free the <hi>States General</hi> from that fear, would promiſe them to attack no places, and to cauſe his Forces to act elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and content himſelf to force the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> by quartering of his Troups on them, and the exacting of Contributions; and what concerned the ſecurity which his Majeſty deſired, that no new Levies ſhould be made, that thoſe were matters that might beſt be by Verbal expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but not mentioned in the Memorial, that thereby the intrinſick of Government ſhould not be touched, but that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95994:12"/>
it would be ſufficient to ſay that they ſhould remain in the State wherein they were, and that alſo otherwiſe when they agreed concerning the reſt, they would then rather think on diſcharging of thoſe already raiſed, than of raiſing any new Troups.</p>
            <p>That the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had very earneſtly preſſed him to obtain that permiſſion of his Majeſty, and that they did all what was poſſible thereby to cauſe that matter to take effect, that they had aſſured him that every day they gained one or other City to their judgment, and that they had gained one of the principalleſt; that they wrought hard to bring the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to an accommodation, and if that could not be effected, that they muſt then take the aforeſaid means in hand to maintain the Peace in the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Netherlands,</hi> and that they hoped that the Provinces of <hi>Frieſland</hi> City and Countrey would agree to their Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that they had deſired him to ſpeak with their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties to confirm them the more. So that the Lord Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour could aſſure his Majeſty that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> did doe all that was in their power, and that they agitated with the other Cities with an incredible zeal and application, and that he could not omit to acquaint his Majeſty that ſome Members of the State had made difficulty to agree that his Majeſty ſhould execute upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> open Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, for that it was impoſſible that theſe Provinces could maintain themſelves, when<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſhould not know from whence to find ſubſiſtence, and that ſo indirectly the whole Barrier ſhould be taken away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Now to conſider whether there be truth in what the Lord Embaſſadour hath written in this matter, you will no doubt remember that the Lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in particular diſcourſes they had with the Members of the Aſſembly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had orderly taken their ſeats, as alſo when the ſame Members were riſen after the concluſion, and demit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95994:12"/>
of the Aſſembly they had now and then ſpoken much of expedients that ought to be taken to keep the War out of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> in caſe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould accept none of the <hi>French Poſtulata,</hi> or accommodate themſelves with <hi>France;</hi> that they alſo endeavoured particularly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves of his Highneſs, whether the Militia of this State in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> had any other order but onely to defend the Cities, and that ſome of them as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before I have ſaid, had named the foreſaid procedures by the <hi>French</hi> in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> a chaſtiſement which <hi>Spain</hi> had well deſerved, and a remedy whereby the King of <hi>Spain</hi> would be obliged to ſubmit to the Will of the King of <hi>France,</hi> and thereby it may be deduced that it is eaſily to be believed that thoſe propoſitions iſſued from thoſe who were poſſeſſed with ſuch an ill will againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſo great a good will for <hi>France,</hi> that all thoſe horrid actions committed in the foreſaid <hi>Netherlands</hi> were onely palliated with the names of chaſtiſements, and looked on as reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to force <hi>Spain</hi> to agree to the Will of <hi>France;</hi> and you are not ignorant how often they in the Aſſembly of the States by their publick advices have ſaid that they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate <hi>Spain</hi> to yield to one of the <hi>French Poſtulata.</hi> And that they have more and more explained themſelves that they thereby underſtood that in relation thereto means muſt be uſed to conſtrain them and make them ſenſible.</p>
            <p>That it is alſo true that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that that which <hi>France</hi> had to propoſe might be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to all the World, thereby to gain their advantage on thoſe who were ignorant, may hereby appear; that when in the Aſſembly of <hi>Holland</hi> they had deliberated on the means of Secreſie which ſhould be obſerved in the Treaties ſet on foot with the Allies concerning the means of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had openly ſaid, that they would not conſent therein, becauſe they would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95994:13"/>
be over-voted by all the other diſſenting Members in the negotiation of that affair, that in that ſame matter they might not make any notes nor relate to others what paſſed therein, and that therefore they rather would the ſame ſhould paſs through a number of above 400 perſons than paſs through a few; out of which, according to my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment nothing elſe is to be concluded, but that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> finding themſelves in their opinion ſingular, and that all the other Members meeting in the Aſſembly much blamed their conduct, though that by thoſe who did not there appear, but daily heard and ſaw what was there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberated on, and who could not ſo well be informed of all things as the others, they would reap more benefit by an abuſive information given them; and to raiſe an agitation in the minds of the Regents and other inhabitants under that pleaſing pretence of Peace and Freedom from extraordinary Taxes, and that they could not ſo well ſerve themſelves thereof when they muſt onely ſpeak to thoſe who were as well informed of theſe matters as themſelves, and could on all occaſions undeniably convince them of their abuſes and wrong propoſitions. For that the Allegation which they made, that this negotiation was of that importance, that the whole Government ought to have cognizance thereof, was but a pretence, will not onely appear that the buſineſs wherein the foreſaid Secreſie ſhould have been uſed, ſhould have onely been preparatory, and not that the Lords there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to appointed ſhould have concluded ought finally without the States of the reſpective Provinces, or thoſe who ſhould be thereunto by them authorized after a full account of what in that affair had paſſed, and with full and conſiderate deliberation ſhould have reſolved and determined what they ſhould have judged to conſiſt with the ſervice of the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; which deſign and intention of theirs appeareth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably, that they themſelves propoſed that when the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95994:13"/>
other Members would conform to their ſentiments, and would joyn with them for the furtherance of a peace, they by writing declared to conſent to leave the direction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to a very few perſons, ſo that no importance in the nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, publick or ſecret direction and ordering concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the furthering thereof, cometh in conſideration, but onely whether the other Members will agree to the ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and then all may paſs, but when that cannot be aſſented to, although all the other Members agree in one ſentiment, nothing muſt paſs how rational ſoever it be, and on whatſoever foregoing examples and practice it may be founded; and concerning the earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and endeavours they have uſed with the other Cities, I need not mention they being ſo known that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> could not deny it; alſo neither the earneſtneſs and endeavours they uſed with the Lord Deputies of the Provinces of <hi>Frieſland</hi> and City and County: You alſo well know that hitherto the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have not conſented to the ordinary and extraordinary State of War, that they might make it appear that it was true which they had promiſed the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour, that if all things ſucceeded to their mind, it would rather be endeavoured to diſcharge, than to raiſe, new Forces, and that when ſome of the Members of the Aſſembly about that time ſpoke with the Lord Penſionary Councellor of <hi>Holland</hi> concerning the Declaration which the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould make to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack no Cities, but onely to execute upon the open Countrey till they ſhould be agreed about a Peace between the two Crowns; the ſaid Lord Penſionary Councellor ſhould have asked theſe Members how and from whence thoſe Cities ſhould be thus ſupplied when the open Countrey was thus ruined, for that it was clear theſe Cities could not ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the open Countrey, and ſo muſt of themſelves fall into the hands of the King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95994:14"/>What farther is contained in the ſaid Letter concerning the deſigned Levy, and the oppoſition of the Lords of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> againſt it; It alſo is true and known, that to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame, the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have uſed all poſſible endeavours, that I need to ſpeak no farther thereof, but I could never have thought that they had done it, induced by the good intentions the King of <hi>France</hi> declared to have towards them, and ſtrengthened by the means which were propounded to them, if the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour had not ſo plainly expreſſed the ſame in the ſaid Letter; and I am the more convinc'd of the truth of the whole contents of the Letter when I remark, firſt that the Lords of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had often asked from whence thoſe Solicitours would get money, when the raiſing of the Forces would be begun without their conſent, and that they in the Aſſembly of the States have by propoſition asked who ſhould bear the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the foreſaid Levy, when they conſented not therein; and ſecondly, that it is true that the <hi>Heer Van Haren</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Embaſſadour of this State to the Court of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> then being here in the <hi>Hague,</hi> and ſpeaking with his Highneſs concerning the neceſſity of the ſaid Levies, and complaining that the deliberations concerning the ſame, proceeded ſo ſlowly, and that the oppoſition of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> againſt the ſaid Levy much hindred the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the other Provinces; whereupon his Highneſs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that he hoped that the Members in <hi>Holland</hi> would make an end thereof, and in few days bring it to a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion if poſſible, with aſſent, if not without the aſſent of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> ſince the Countrey muſt not be deprived of their defence for obſtinateneſs of one Member; and laſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that the ſaid Embaſſadour writeth, <hi>viz.</hi> that he as yet deſired not to know of his Majeſty what ſecurity he ſhould demand of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in caſe they could not move the States to conſent to thoſe things his Majeſty
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95994:14"/>
deſired of them, becauſe he knew not what therein his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie's intentions might be, that he the Lord Embaſſadour could onely ſay, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon not yet explained themſelves to him, and that they had expreſly ſaid to him, that they were remedies to which no recourſe ought to be had but in the utmoſt extremity, that they would not ſpeak to him concerning the ſame, till they had loſt all hope to give to his Majeſty by the States that ſecurity which ought to be given him, which they yet ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to be able to effect, and though I readily yield that to be very hardly believed, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhould be able to arrive to ſuch an extravagancy, yet I muſt confeſs I ought not to doubt thereof, when I conſider not onely the diſcourſes which the ſaid Members at this time often have maintained, namely, that if they were not conſented to, that they then muſt conſider their own ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; yea, that they alſo ſo far expreſt themſelves that when the other Members required that the matter of the Levy ſhould be brought to a concluſion, that they in their turn giving in their advice in the Aſſembly of the States publickly had dared to ſay, that they underſtood not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in a Society wherein they enjoyed not the right of that Society, not conſidering that the Body of the Sovereignty of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Frieſland</hi> was not brought together as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Members united by ſpecial contract, as the union of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> brought the ſeveral Provinces together, but in a manner, of which no particular account can be given, onely that in the old Hiſtories it is ſaid, that the City of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in its beginning was under the power and direction of particular Lords, who were alſo at that time Subjects to the Earls of <hi>Holland;</hi> whereas the ancient Hiſtories mention not that ſeveral other Cities were under the like ſubjection to other Lords alſo ſubject, but immediately under the Earls of <hi>Holland,</hi> and have thus immediately from the beginning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95994:15"/>
compoſed the Body of the States, whereas the City of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> could not enjoy that honour during they were under thoſe particular ſubject Lords; beſides that every one muſt think it ſtrange that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining that the ſaid Levy was concluded without their conſent, and would ſay that the right of the Society was not yielded them, whereas the Body of the Sovereignty of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Frieſland</hi> being obliged for the conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Religion and Freedom to the Land to their utmoſt power; that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> by a ſtrange obſtinateneſs refuſed to help to provide what all the other its Members judged indiſpenſably neceſſary for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon defence, and in a time when all their Neighbours round about ſtrongly armed, did more and more ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then themſelves by new Levies, and all the friends of this State had their eyes on the reſolutions of this State, for the defence of it ſelf againſt oppreſſion and over-ruling, and with God's bleſſing to free itſelf therefrom; and of which in that ſad year of 1672. they had experimented ſo great and ſenſible a fuſſerance, for having neglected the putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a poſture of defence.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe in what hath been ſaid, I have clearly ſhewed that what the ſaid Embaſſadour hath expreſt in the ſaid Letter, is not onely very probable, but as evident as things of that nature can be made, and that there is therein no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe of doubt when it may be ſeen what ſince the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the aforeſaid Letter by the forementioned Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour farther hath been done, namely, that the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour having by the aforeſaid Letter earneſtly deſired that his Majeſty would give him ſome permiſſion to preſent Memorials, and particularly that he ſhould not need there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to expreſs of the not making the ſaid Levy; and that he might therein uſe ſome ſweetnings in conſideration of the open Countrey of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> firſt by a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95994:15"/>
Memorial the Nineteenth of this Month, preſented to the States, hath declared that he would take it on himſelf to grant ſome time to bring the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to an accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the conditions propoſed by his Majeſty, if they would promiſe his Majeſty to remain in the State where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were without making any ſteps which might make the <hi>Spaniards</hi> more obſtinate by the hopes of a new and greater ſuccour: and then afterwards, firſt in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference (which he willingly would have had on the Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of the ſaid Month, but which was had on the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, for that the Deputies of <hi>Holland</hi> who were alſo to be at the ſame, aſſiſted on the aforeſaid Sixteenth of <hi>February,</hi> at the deliberation which then was had in <hi>Holland</hi> on the aforeſaid Letter of the Lord Embaſſadour) and hath after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards declared by a Memorial, that in caſe the States would engage to cauſe <hi>Spain</hi> to agree within two or three Months to one of the Equivalents contained in the aforeſaid Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of the Fifth of <hi>November</hi> laſt, or a Truce of Twenty years, that his Majeſty would ceaſe all Hoſtilities againſt the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> but ſo that if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould ſuffer thoſe two or three Months to run out without effect, that then the States ſhould cauſe that their Troups now in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> ſhould not be otherwiſe employed than in defence of the places his Majeſty of <hi>Spain</hi> there poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth, that they alſo ſhould promiſe to give no where elſe any aſſiſtence to <hi>Spain</hi> againſt his Majeſty of <hi>France</hi> or his Allyes, and that then <hi>France</hi> would promiſe to Beſiege or take no places in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> yea not to act the War any more on the open Countrey on condition that <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould alſo obſerve the ſame, and reſerving to himſelf to uſe his Arms elſewhere till that Crown ſhould compoſe the Peace which it had broken. Or if the States would not oblige themſelves thereto, and would onely uſe earneſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to preſs <hi>Spain</hi> to a friendly accommodation, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95994:16"/>
alſo in ſuch a caſe his Majeſty would yield to a Ceſſation of Arms in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> as long as the preſent War ſhould laſt, and alſo promiſe neither by Siege or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to make himſelf Maſter of any places in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands;</hi> provided that the States on the contrary ſhould oblige themſelves not onely that their Troups in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> ſhould onely be employed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the places in the ſaid <hi>Netherlands,</hi> but that alſo they ſhould give <hi>Spain</hi> no farther aſſiſtance in any other place whatſoever, nor to act directly nor indirectly againſt his Majeſty or his Allies; and that alſo his Majeſty would oblige himſelf to perform no acts of Hoſtility in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> provided <hi>Spain</hi> ſhall from the ſaid <hi>Netherlands</hi> act no Hoſtility againſt him, or if it would there continue the War, that his Majeſty would then conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue it there onely againſt the open Countrey, for what can better agree with what the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Lord Embaſſadour, they ſay there muſt be no ſpeech of making no new Levies, but to leave matters in the ſame ſtate they were in? He doth alſo the ſame by his firſt Memorial. They ſay there ſhould be a Ceſſation of Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity againſt the Cities in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> provided that the State meddle not with the Quarrel elſewhere, or elſewhere help <hi>Spain,</hi> he doth ſo likewiſe, and for that he feared it would offend, that that Ceſſation of Hoſtility ſhould not extend to the benefit of the open Countrey; he profereth the ſame alſo for ſo much as concerneth the open countrey, if <hi>Spain</hi> on its part will not from the <hi>Netherlands</hi> act ought on the open countrey of the <hi>French.</hi> He preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth alſo thoſe Memorials as late as he can, and then when he judgeth that he would be thereby ſitted to ſupport the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in their deſigns, ſo that none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand not prejudiced, can deny or doubt in his mind that what is contained in the aforeſaid Letter is in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95994:16"/>
truth for ſo much as concerneth the eſſential part, not come to paſs and effected.</p>
            <p>That being ſo, we may conſider whether the Lords of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> may not be ſaid to have there in done amiſs, yea great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done amiſs. I believe not that the ſaid Lords will them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves call in doubt that what is ſaid in the foreſaid Letter to have been done by them ſhould not contain offences hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the utmoſt to the greatneſs and juſtneſs of the State, and the welfare thereof, and capable to cauſe the ruine of the Countrey; for what can be more hurtfull and hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the State that at this time (when we ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour either an accommodation between parties at War to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or muſt experience the loſs of the <hi>Spaniſh Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> or to fall in difference concerning the ſame with the King of <hi>France,</hi> and that as well the loſs of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> as the falling at odds with the King of <hi>France,</hi> would be very prejudicial to the State) they ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulary diſcover to the King of <hi>France,</hi> or that which is the ſame to his Embaſſadour the difference which was in the State between the Members thereof about finding out means of accommodation; that the one was of advice, that to put our ſelves in ſecurity of not being ſurprized, was by raiſing a greater number of <hi>Militia,</hi> and then to ſpeak and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for a good and laſting accommodation; and that others adviſed that without providing any means of Defence, they muſt blindfold help to execute what <hi>France</hi> deſired of <hi>Spain.</hi> That the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſaid they would never yield to a Levy, but to doe what might be done to oblige <hi>Spain</hi> to accept one of the <hi>French</hi> propoſals, for that theſe communications could indeed be of no other effect than more and more to encourage <hi>France</hi> to yield in nothing of what he pretended, and to draw <hi>Spain</hi> more and more off, and make him averſe from all that by this State ſhould be propoſed to him to the furtherance of a Peace; for ſince
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95994:17"/>
the mediation of the Peace depended not on the will of this State, but on the approbation of <hi>Spain,</hi> for that all what <hi>France</hi> pretendeth whether out of the head of his firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, or by conſequence of the Equivalents, whereof was pertaining to <hi>Spain,</hi> and by that King muſt be yielded, and that <hi>Spain</hi> was ſo perſwaded that that which <hi>France</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded was ſo unjuſt, that <hi>Spain</hi> deſired that his Allies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether would examine whether the foreſaid pretenſions were founded on reaſon, adding, that if they ſhould judge the ſaid pretenſions were juſt, he would much yield in ſuch a caſe to the judgment of his Allies, we could in ſuch a caſe never make this State more unfit to uſe endeavours with <hi>Spain</hi> for an accommodation, than to declare to <hi>France</hi> that we ſhould force <hi>Spain</hi> to the acceptance of one of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid propoſitions, that we inceſſantly endeavoured the ſame, employing all our credit to make diſputes in the Cities, and alſo withhold what in caſe of need might ſerve us in ſome meaſure to defend the State, to wit the Levy of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Men. And what could more move <hi>France</hi> to yield nothing, as being aſcertained, not from without or from ſome out of the Government, but of ſuch a conſiderable Member of the ſame Government, that the ſaid Member uſed its utmoſt endeavours with an incredible zeal and application to bring <hi>Spain</hi> to accept one of the foreſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals, and to withhold that which in any manner might ſerve to put off the firſt puſh, if no accommodation could have been made with <hi>France,</hi> which was the foreſaid new Levies, ſince <hi>France</hi> was thereby aſſured that <hi>Spain</hi> muſt either yield to the aforeſaid conditions, or that otherwiſe he finding <hi>Spain</hi> and this State without any power to reſiſt, and giving him all opportunity with the approaching Spring to ſettle and bring to effect his deſigns to poſſeſs himſelf not onely of the foreſaid <hi>Netherlands,</hi> but alſo of this State; I leave it to the judgment of wiſer perſons, if this be not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95994:17"/>
criminal and deſerving puniſhment in the higheſt, for that it hurteth to the utmoſt the ſecurity of the State, by diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the weakneſs thereof to thoſe whom the State ought chiefly to fear, and animated them withall not to diminiſh of his demands, and put a ſufficient opportunity into his hands of carrying the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> to the utmoſt detriment of this State, if not this State it ſelf at laſt. Secondly it appeareth by the aforeſoid Letter, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in conſult with the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and animated by the kindneſs the King of <hi>France</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to have for them, and fortified by the means he propoſed to them, had openly withſtood the ſaid Levy and cauſed many Diſputes in ſeveral of the Cities concerning the ſame; you may, Sir, hereby judge whether it be not criminal to raiſe diſputes among the Members of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and animated thereto by the ſervice a Foreign Prince pretendeth they doe him therein, and ſtrengthned by the means which that Foreign Prince propoſeth; yea, and that of a Prince who by his Forces hath attacked an Allye of this State, in a place in which the State hath ſo ſenſible an intereſt, and whither the State hath ſent aſſiſtence to that Allye ſo attacked, and theſe ſaid aſſiſting Troups are actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally employed to the aſſiſtence of the Attacked againſt the Attacker, and that theſe diſputes are occaſions to put and keep the State out of a poſture of needfull defence.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have, if not perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, yet openly concerted with the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour concerning overtures whereby this State ſhould be engaged either to force <hi>Spain</hi> to accept one of the <hi>French</hi> propoſals, or to deſert them on condition onely that <hi>France</hi> ſhould leave the places in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> unattacked and continue to moleſt the open Countrey with Quarterings and Contributions; that they had earneſtly inſiſted that he would preſent a Memorial to that effect whereby they would be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95994:18"/>
in a condition to effect the buſineſs; if that be not alſo cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal and puniſhable in the higheſt degree, I willingly leave to the cenſure of wiſer and ſharper judgments. I very well know how that matter was reſented in the year 1666. and what Letters ſome Miniſters of this State, being then in <hi>France,</hi> have written notwithſtanding that what then paſſed hath no more compariſon with this preſent affair, than a Gnat to an Elephant; for what can be more hurtfull and diſadvantageous to the greatneſs of this State, than that a Member of one Province by particular authority, without knowledge of its other Fellow Members, ſhould in ſuch a manner deal with a Foreign Prince who hath Attacked one of the Allyes of the State, who muſt be aſſiſted by that State, and is already actually aſſiſted, and ſhould confer with that Foreign Prince, not onely to make ineffec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, but even to break the Treaty the State hath made with the Attacked? where is it (wherein the State muſt find its ſecurity, (as the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have often ſaid) by Allyances and Contracts with Foreign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the over power of others, which by their own power they cannot effect;) and what can bring ſuch Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyances and contracts in more diſcredit with Foreign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than that they ſhall perceive that it is in the power of one Province, yea, of one Member of a Province by its own <hi>Capricio</hi> to make ineffectual Treaties ſolemnly made, or to withhold the effect thereof? and how can it be born by the Supreme Authority, that whereas by the conſtitution of the Government of theſe Countreys, one Province alone (how Sovereign ſoever it be) cannot enter into Treaties with Foreign Princes; that one Member of a Province, to wit, the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhall propoſe or at leaſt concert with the ſaid Embaſſadour without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Government concerning ſuch overtures of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95994:18"/>
and deſire him to propoſe the ſame by a Memorial, and that they hope by that means to bring them to effect? I will not now ſpeak of the Propoſals themſelves ſo diſhonourable and ſo unfit, that every one that hath yet remaining in him but a ſmall portion of Fidelity and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, muſt have for the ſame the utmoſt abhorrence; for what can be more diſhonourably imagined, than that this State which is obliged to defend <hi>Spain</hi> againſt unjuſt Force, ſhould by a publick Treaty oblige it ſelf to force <hi>Spain</hi> to that which <hi>France</hi> alone by force and over power acquireth of <hi>Spain</hi> (as <hi>Spain</hi> ſays) and not by Right and Juſtice, and that in a time when <hi>Spain</hi> will permit this State to examine the juſtice or injuſtice of the <hi>French</hi> pretenſions, or if they could not arrive thereto, that by a publick Treaty they ſhould oblige themſelves to give <hi>Spain</hi> over to the will of <hi>France;</hi> and that in all parts of the World <hi>France</hi> might at his pleaſure exerciſe all force and wrong on <hi>Spain,</hi> onely that the Cities in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> might not be At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked, yea, that in the ſame <hi>Netherlands</hi> they might act on the open Countrey theſe horrible ſorts of executions of which in former Wars hath not been heard? In truth if this conduct of affairs had not been ſo publickly and clearly ſeen, it could not be imagined that ſuch a Government as is that of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhould have arrived ſo far, to give ſo evident a proof of a perfidiouſneſs ſo great and unheard of. I cannot deny that it may ſometimes have happened that one hath left his Friend and Allye in need, and although it be very ill done, and that God hath often ſadly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch perfidiouſneſs, yet hath the deſerter always found or made a pretence to colour that his ſaying, that he could no longer aſſiſt his Friend; but ſo far as I can remember no inſtance can be found that a Prince or State without any the leaſt reaſon ſhould oblige himſelf by a particular Treaty, to force his Friend to yield to what is unjuſtly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95994:19"/>
required of him or to give him over, to the pleaſure of his oppoſite party, when the oppoſite party hath not put that his pleaſure in execution in preſence of the deſerter of his Friend; beſides that when that ſcandalous and diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing could not produce that expected effect, for that <hi>Spain</hi> finding it ſelf treated in ſuch a baſe manner one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> might remain ſafe, and that thereby the War would but the more furiouſly be tranſported to his other Countries and Kingdoms would ſoon find means to ſecure himſelf from that danger by a yielding over or changing theſe Countreys which they deſire to preſerve in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> for that which <hi>Spain</hi> in former Wars had now or formerly loſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It appeareth by the foreſaid Letter that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had ſpoke with the ſaid Lord Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſladour concerning the ſecurity which they in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar were to give, if the State ſhould not approve to yield thoſe matters his Majeſty had propoſed. You may, Sir, eaſily conceive that this is not a leſs but at leaſt as great a crime as any of the forementioned, for how can it agree with the Majeſty of the State, that one of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame ſhould give ſecurity to a Foreign Prince to effect that the State ſhould grant thoſe conditions which the ſaid Foreign Prince deſireth of them, yea, how can it be ſuffered by a Sovereign State, that one of the Members ſhall comprehend all the reſt, or if that cannot be effected, ſhall engage it ſelf to agree apart concerning other particular Securities which this Member ſhould then give to a Foreign Prince?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, by the ſaid Letter it alſo appeareth, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign on foot to cauſe the ſaid Embaſſadour to preſent the foreſaid Memorial, was to raiſe the good Subjects againſt the Government, as if the Government were inclined to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95994:19"/>
War, and that the King of <hi>France</hi> preſented and Proffered Peace, and that the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> lending thereto their helping hand, ſought to evade the War, and that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the other Members who in that matter could not joyn with the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſought to engage the State in a ſad and deplorable War, whereas his Highneſs and all the Members compoſing the Aſſembly of States have often declared with the utmoſt ſincerity, that they deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing elſe than if it were any ways poſſible to help to allay theſe differences by an accommodation, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſent conſtitution of times and matters might be in any manner eſteemed honourable and ſecure; and that they would concerning the ſame, enter into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with <hi>Spain,</hi> and the other their high Allyes, ſince unto <hi>Spain</hi> belonged that which ſhould be ſacrificed to the Peace; and that by the aforeſaid written Letter no ſecurity for Peace was made, neither could be, if it were not ſecured by a good Guaranty of other Princes and States, and that for the obtaining that Guaranty there was nothing to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected or hoped, if concerning that Peace there were no conſultation with the ſaid high Allyes, and they induced to the conditions thereof, yea, to hear all the Members who frequented the Aſſembly; alſo the Lords deputed of the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have often been neceſſitated to acknowledge that all the meaſures his Highneſs took were towards a Peace, and that his Highneſs had not given to any of them reaſons to ſuſpect that he was not inclined to a Peace: And, Sir, you know what reaſon I have to be well perſwaded, that the Peace had been long ſince attained, at leaſt would have been much furthered, and that the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Country would have had much leſs trouble if the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> by their conduct had not given <hi>France</hi> cauſe to hope to obtain better conditions than could be effected, and had thereby made on the one ſide all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95994:20"/>
and inducement, which could have been made with <hi>Spain</hi> invalid, and on the other ſide ſtirr'd up <hi>France</hi> to yield nothing, and to quit nothing of his Demands and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals by him made as conditions of Peace; yea, Sir, you well know that when here in the <hi>Hague</hi> entrance was made into a Treaty with <hi>Spain,</hi> and the other high Allyes who had here expreſly their Miniſters to enter into a Conference of Propoſals for accommodation, that on the part of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in the Aſſembly of the States, where (in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the confidence and ſecurity which ſhould be among Allyes and friends, having one and the ſame deſign) then concerning the keeping ſecret, not of that which ſhould be brought to a concluſion, for that was proffered to be made known when it was proper, but of that which in that Conference might happen, yet without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding; and then concerning many Queſtions, Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and the like, which could not but cauſe a great ſuſpicion, and alienate the minds of the high Allyes, from one another, there hath often ſuch Propoſitions iſſued forth from which nothing elſe could be concluded but that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> muſt have had a deſign to ſmother the ſaid Conference in the beginning, and to make it fruitleſs; and that the other Members of the States Aſſembly were in this their conduct, and ſo acting much diſſatisfied, and have much blamed them all, none excepted.</p>
            <p>I muſt, Sir, ask you whether a rational man, and who is a lover of the welfare of his Countrey, and of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and freedom in ſo great eſteem with our Forefathers ſhall be found, who ſeeing ſuch a Letter written by an Embaſſadour, who hath managed the affairs of his Maſter in this Countrey ſo many years, and hath been before em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the like affairs, ſeeing and knowing that what is written in the ſaid Letter ſo well agreeth with that which hath happened and was tranſacted even by the ſaid Lords
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95994:20"/>
of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> as here before at large I have demonſtrated and knowing that that which was contained in the ſaid Letter, if it agreed with the truth, was in the higheſt criminal and puniſhable, and that this Republick could not ſubſiſt, but muſt periſh if ſuch tranſactions were tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that every Member who could not in Aſſembly effect the matter to his deſire, might concert with the Miniſters of Foreign Princes, and joyn with them, and conclude how beſt to oblige the other Members thereto, would not doe at leaſt ſo much as to contribute what could be thought thereof to attain the truth contained in that Letter, and ſince it could from nowhere elſe better appear than out of the Papers which poſſibly might be found in the Lodgings of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> here in the <hi>Hague,</hi> and in the Chamber of the Lord Councellor Penſionary <hi>Hop,</hi> who had for the moſt part held the conferences with the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour, and where the Members knew that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had cauſed the continuance of thoſe Conferences, notwithſtanding the other Members had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to be offended and ſcandalized thereat, whether they were not alſo obliged to take care that thoſe Papers ſhould be ſealed, to the end the States, after all the depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Lords ſhould have made their report to the Lords their Principals, might be in condition to deliberate and reſolve on what they ſhould find expedient to have done or left therein, for that is all that hitherto hath been done, or ordained by the States, <hi>viz.</hi> that the foreſaid over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which his Highneſs ſhould make, ſhould be received with cloſed doors, that the mentioned Lords <hi>Hooft</hi> and <hi>Hop</hi> ſhould abſent while his Highneſs made the ſame over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the foreſaid Papers ſhould be ſealed up, that the whole overture ſhould be kept Secret, except that thereof was to be given notice to the Councils of the ſeveral Cities, and of the ſealing of them onely to the Lords Burgomaſters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95994:21"/>
and all this upon Oath, that the ſaid matter might be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged with as little noiſe as was poſſible, till the reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Burgomaſters and Councils having had knowledge of all things might diſpoſe of Affairs, and if the Lords Burgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters and Council of the foreſaid City, had not onely been the firſt who had writ their foreſaid Letter to the other Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, but alſo connived at the publick Printing thereof, the aforeſaid matter might have been as little noiſed abroad as other matters which in the like manner were debated in the Aſſembly with ſhut doors in ſecret, and without noiſe. But it is ſaid that hereby is deminiſhed the freedom and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity which thoſe Deputies who were in the Aſſembly ought to enjoy as to their perſons and Papers: For what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the perſons, the complaint is yet too unripe, for againſt the perſons of the ſaid Lords Deputies hath nothing been determined, but I would have asked whether thoſe who are deputed to the Aſſembly have thereby a licence to commit and act whatſoever they think good without being for the ſame ſearched or puniſhed; I believe not that it will be ſaid by any, at leaſt thoſe that would ſay it, muſt then ſuppoſe that thoſe deputed to ſuch an Aſſembly might alſo ſell their Countrey to the Enemy; and that the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of States which is deſigned for the good of the Countrey, and is ſo needfull and ſerviceable for the peace and conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the ſame, might produce the hurtfulleſt effects to the ſaid Countrey without means of puniſhing ſuch evil doers, and thoſe who abuſed the freedom of ſuch an Aſſembly in ſuch an unfit and diſhonourable way; but that being otherwiſe, and the foreſaid Aſſembly being onely deſigned to prevent any ill effect that might accrue to the Commonwealth, therefore thoſe who under pretence of ſuch an Aſſembly, and that they are Members thereof when they ſhall come to contrive ſuch matters as onely tend to the ſubverſion of the liberty, and the ruine of their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95994:21"/>
Countrey muſt not think they may evade by a fair pretence of liberty and freedom, the ſearch which their Lawfull and Sovereign Authority doth reſolve to make; but it is ſaid the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> were not admitted to make their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in relation to the contents of the ſaid Letter. But I leave it to your judgment how juſtly this is objected, for the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> complain now that the Nobility and the other Deputies, whereof the Aſſembly of the States was then compoſed, did reſolve to ſeal up thoſe Papers, the ſealing up whereof was performed in that manner, which was leaſt offenſive, the ſame ſealing up of them being onely a mere ſecuring of them, and had no communication with any criminal proceſs; The Lords Deputies leaving all matters as they were, that when the reſpective Councels of the Cities ſhould have had cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of what had paſſed, they might deliberate what was to be done, <hi>viz.</hi> whether they ſhould proceed to a farther examination either of the foreſaid ſealed Papers, or to hear and examine thoſe who had held thoſe Conferences with the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour, and alſo of others who might be detected to have had knowledge thereof. If they had proceeded to the hearing of the ſaid Lords, would it not then have been ſaid that the Aſſembly of the States had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to begin a criminal proceſs by the examination of the ſaid Lords which the ſaid Aſſembly ought not to doe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſeat of Juſtice? and what more might be ſaid to that purpoſe. It is further ſaid concerning the forementioned Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> that this Letter was writ by a Foreign Miniſter, which could import nothing to the hurt of a third Perſon; but it was alſo true that the Writer thereof was an Embaſſadour who gave an account to his King, and who was obliged to give that account in the beſt and trueſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; it appeared alſo out of that Letter how neatly he therein diſtinguiſhed what the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95994:22"/>
with him what they had propoſed to him, and what they had undertaken to effect and further what was known to him of the matter under diſpute, whatſoever ſenſe he had thereof, the duties he had to obſerve with them, and the duty in which he was obliged to his Maſter, and eſpecially that his Majeſty was therein in the higheſt concerned, that he might know and be well informed of all what paſſed here, and that he therefore to know his Majeſty's intentions on what he had written, had ſent the ſaid Letter with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs; he was alſo a Miniſter who kept with the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> a perfect friendſhip and correſpondency, who by their councel had been to confer with the other Members of the Aſſembly, and again with whom the Lords of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> uſed ſo great confidence that they would rather load on themſelves the ſcandal and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſuſpicion of the other Members of the States Aſſembly than to miſs the ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; but it is ſaid the deſign was Peace, and all the Members profeſſed their inclination thereto, and it was not prohibited to correſpond with ſuch Foreign Miniſters whoſe Maſters were in friendſhip with this State. As concerning the matter of the Peace I have ſpoken before, and alſo ſhewed it to be a <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis</hi> in the firſt and higheſt degree to undertake ſuch negotiations as are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſaid Letter which the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had held with the ſaid Lord the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour; it cannot alſo not be thought by any one that it ſhould be lawfull in a State obliged to one another in ſuch manner, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing one body of Government as doth this State, that one Member of one of the Members of that Body ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all the other Members in matters of Peace, wherein all the others cannot comprehend that one Member; and I would that any one were found ſo underſtanding and ſharp witted who ſhould then tell me what a Government we had in this Countrey, where was the Sovereign Power lodged, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95994:22"/>
with whom men had to treat and contract, and how far might extend the Capricios of one Member who deſigneth to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh it ſelf from all the other Members, each of which hath the ſame right with this Member, and who eſteem themſelves as good Patriots of their Countrey, as that one Member, and to be as much inclined to Peace as that one ſeparate Member, and who would treat and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract with a Government conſtituted in that manner. I will not now enter into the Examination, whether and how far Members of the ſame Government may undertake to correſpond with Miniſters of Foreign Princes, and how that is underſtood in this Republick, but I will onely ſay that I have ſeen when the Queen of <hi>England</hi> in the year 1588. endeavoured to treat of Peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> and that in that matter there was there in this Countrey no ſmall diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Aſſembly of <hi>Holland,</hi> that the Members thereof were not onely obliged to abſtain from all correſpondence, but were alſo obliged to diſcover all what occurred to them even from that Queen or any one whomſoever of her Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, notwithſtanding we were in a very ſtrict Allyance with her Majeſty, and had from her Majeſty an actual aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, and had alſo two Councellors of her Majeſty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in our Council of State, to whom then the greateſt part of the direction of Affairs was imparted; but the matter is not whether any Member of the State keep correſpondence with a Foreign Miniſter, but whether it may be permitted to any Member of the Government whatſoever to keep ſuch correſpondences as are mentioned in the foreſaid Letter. It is further ſaid that it was onely uncifered, and which the Marquis <hi>de Grana</hi> had ſent, 'tis true it was ſent by the Marquis <hi>de Grana</hi> as having intercepted it, and conceived the State to be ſo much concerned therein, that it ought to know what was here contriving to the detriment of the Publick, but the ſaid Marquis <hi>de Grana</hi> whoſe uprightneſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95994:23"/>
ſome would queſtion, hath proceeded therein with that candour that he alſo ſent hither the Key whereby he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifered the Letter, that it might appear by what Rule they uncifered the ſame, and that it was impoſſible to feign the like, as they now endeavour to make it ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>To which is added, that the Lords deputed from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> to the Aſſembly of <hi>States</hi> having underſtood that the Lord Embaſſadour had ſome Propoſals to make, whereby the Peace in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> and between <hi>France</hi> and this State might be preſerved, and that he was deſirous to confer with them concerning the ſame; that they had made report thereof to the Lords their Principals with many circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, who had eſpecially charged them to have a nearer Conference with the Lord Embaſſadour concerning the ſame, and oblige him to give notice thereof to the Members, and eſpecially to the Lord Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as the Miniſter of the Lords the Nobles, and that the ſaid Lords deputed of the ſaid City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had alſo given notice thereof to the ſaid Lord Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Holland;</hi> but hereon I will firſt ask wherefore the Lords deputed from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> were ſo ſcrupulous to hear and receive ſuch Propoſals of the ſaid Embaſſadour, if there had been nothing elſe to treat between them, and that they charged the other Members who had no order from their Principals with the having viſited the ſaid Lord Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and to have heard the ſaid Propoſals of him, for they ſay that they were thoſe, who would have had that they ſhould alſo ſpeak to the other Members, whereas before they had made no difficulty to ſpeak to ſo many other Foreign Miniſters, without having had ſuch ſpecial charge from their Principals, and ſaid with ſo much aſſurance even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the diſpleaſure therein of the other Members, they both ſhould and would continue the ſaid Conferences with the ſaid Embaſſadour, and notwithſtanding the foreſaid
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95994:23"/>
narration of that Conference is clearly and at large made appear, even as if the ſaid Lords Deputies had given to the States in the Aſſembly a full and perfect knowledge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation thereof, whereas all thoſe know who have been in that Aſſembly, that the ſaid Lords had given to the ſaid Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, not the leaſt knowledge thereof: what here and there they might by particular diſcourſes have ſaid to ſome one or other of the particular Members I know not; it may be they may have to every one given ſuch an overture there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as they thought might ſerve their deſign. You know, Sir, that the Lord Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> hath ſaid more than once, that the ſaid Lords deputed had not in the leaſt made him acquainted therewith, but onely that the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour had alſo ſaid to him the Lord Councellor Penſionary in the aforeſaid Viſit, that in caſe the Lords the States would treat to preſerve the Peace in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> and leave his Majeſty free to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his pretenſions on <hi>Spain</hi> elſewhere, and that they would engage themſelves in ſuch a caſe to afford no aſſiſtance to <hi>Spain,</hi> that his Majeſty would not be averſe thereto; and that the ſaid Lord Councellor Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> had anſwered either to the ſaid deputed Lords, or to the ſaid Lord Penſionary <hi>Hop,</hi> that there could be no delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration had concerning the ſame before a Memorial to that effect was preſented, and that it would occaſion a very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable name to this Republick, with all Foreign Princes, if we ſhould ſo deal with thoſe with whom we were in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance: and you know, Sir, that the ſaid Lord Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> hath alſo often declared that the ſaid Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted except that one time, and in that manner had never given him any other information of the ſaid overture of the ſaid Treaties and Conferences. The ſaid Lord Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> hath not to my knowledge ever pretended that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> were obliged to give him any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95994:24"/>
of what they did, and it will therefore appear as ſtrange to him as to any other, that the ſaid Lords did now appeal to the knowledge they ſhould have given him thereof. What is further ſaid of the cutting off of correſpondence with foreign Miniſters; I know that to have proceeded from the ſo much offending Conferences, which the ſaid Lords deputed had with the forementioned Lord Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. You alſo know, Sir, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have explain'd themſelves thereon to the Aſſembly, in a manner ſo irreverently, that all the Members thereof were thereat highly offended, however none then knew or could ſurmiſe from whence that proceeded, and what was then ordered concerning the diſcourſe relating to the ſhip <hi>La Reigle,</hi> and that on the 8th of <hi>January</hi> laſt, the ſaid Lords deputed had ſpoken with the forementioned Lord Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, ſheweth clearly the deſign contrived with him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the foreſaid matter of which before larger mention is made, and alſo how abuſively and captiouſly, they would excuſe themſelves for having held the ſaid Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences mentioned in the ſaid Letter, when the ſaid Lord Penſionary of <hi>Holland</hi> miſtaking in the date, ſaid, that the foreſaid Conference ſhould have been held on the 9th, whereas it was held on the 8th as is noted in the ſaid Letter; and it is not a little remarkable that the ſaid Lords of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> having firſt ſaid, that the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour of <hi>France</hi> had not urged them to enter into any concern or particular engagement, they notwithſtanding in the ſame breath add, that he the Lord Embaſſadour having preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ſecured by word of mouth of the conſtant incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of that Government to the Peace, and that they would enter into the expedients by him propoſed, that they had often roundly refuſed it notwithſtanding he expreſt his diſpleaſure therein in ſharp terms, ſo that the ſaid Lords do thereby acknowledge that there had been a Speech con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95994:24"/>
ſuch a ſecurity by the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour when they ſay, he demanded the ſame of them, and they denied it, and then alſo when the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour ſhewed his diſpleaſure thereat in ſharp terms; and the ſaid Embaſſadour ſaith alſo in the ſaid Letter, not that the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> had engaged themſelves to give particular ſecurity, but onely ſimply that they had ſaid, that there were remedies to which no recourſe was to be had but in the utmoſt extremity, and that they would not ſpeak with him thereof till they had left all hope of moving the States to aſſent to that ſecurity his Majeſty deſired.</p>
            <p>This being a true recital of what paſſed in the Aſſembly of the States on the 16th of this Month, as alſo of what happened about the conduct which the ſaid Lords of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> were pleaſed to obſerve; and concerning what far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſed, and by undeniable conſequences muſt be dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from thence, I leave it to the judgment of every one if in theſe matters in the procedures againſt the Lords deputed of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> there hath appeared any rigour, prejudice or unbeſeemingneſs, and if they have not abuſed the State and Fellow-members in an unheard of and inſufferable manner, and if thoſe Lords which then compoſed that Aſſembly, and who with ſo much circumſpection proceeded to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſealing up of their Papers were rather to be condemned, that in a matter ſo important and ſuch a high nature they uſed not more vigour for the conſervation of the right of their State againſt thoſe who had proceeded in ſuch an unworthy manner to the ruine of the ſaid State, and who had ſo criminally acted therein, and more than once made themſelves guilty of <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> and whether the good Inhabitants of the Countrey have not the greateſt reaſon to complain that ſuch a chief Member of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as is the Government of the City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> could fall into ſo pernicious a conduct, that they would cut off
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95994:25"/>
and ſeparate themſelves from their other fellow Members; and that all this is vented among the good Inhabitants with ſo much untruth as if the Government of the foreſaid City had in this matter no quarrel with their fellow Members, but onely with his Highneſs, to make all his actions every where odious, and to decry them down, whereas all the Members of the States Aſſembly, none excepted, have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with his Highneſs in the ſame ſentiment, as well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſaid Levy, as concerning the promoting of an accommodation; that they all, none excepted, have highly blamed and been ſcandalized at the conduct of the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and whereas the moderateſt of them who had laboured to find out expedients to allay, and remove if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible the ſaid differences ſo hurtfull and ruinous to this State, were convinced that on the part of his Highneſs all hath been done which hath been required of him, and that this condeſcenſion hath onely extended to confirm the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in their difference, as if the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the State had been ſolely intruſted to them, and that all the other Members muſt yield to them. The length of this diſcourſe troubleth me, but I thought I ought once to let you ſee without any diſguiſement, and in all truth, the matter which here being related as it hath paſſed, can by none who was in the Aſſembly be contradicted as to the truth of the affair.</p>
            <closer>I ſhall always remain, <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed> Your humble Servant, PHILALETHES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:95994:25"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>AFter I had witten the aforeſaid, there came to my hands a Memorial preſented to this State by the Count <hi>D'Avaux</hi> Embaſſadour of the King of <hi>France</hi> the 28th of this Month; I acknowledge I could never have thought that a Lord of ſo great a capacity and experience could have reſolved to preſent a Memorial of that kind, and that the zeal for defending the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> who have ſo much miſtaken themſelves, and acted in ſuch a criminal manner againſt the Majeſty and Sovereignty of the State, had ſo far prevailed with him thus to expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as appeareth by the ſaid Memorial, which alſo more and more confirmeth the ſaid correſpondency, and more and more accuſeth the ſaid Lords. The firſt thing that the Lord Embaſſadour in the ſaid Memorial ſaith is in effect (what he had ſaid by word of mouth to thoſe deputed by the Lords the States who were with him in Conference) that he had informed his Majeſty of the matter, as in truth it was, but in that manner as he ſuppoſed he muſt repreſent it to his Maſter; and that he therefore in that Letter had alledged many circumſtances which agreed not with the truth of the matter. For firſt, what can more ſtrongly ſerve to deſtroy all the Conferences that he had with him the Lord Embaſſadour, and which he ſhould repreſent to his Maſter, according to the truth what had therein paſſed, when the ſaid Embaſſadour by a formal Memorial, ſaith, that he repreſented the matter to his Maſter, not as they are, but as he judged it beſt to repreſent it, and who will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ſo conſiderable a perſon having the honour to ſerve ſuch a King ſhould take upon him to relate matters
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:95994:26"/>
in another form than in truth they were acted; yea, who will believe that in this Relation he hath ſo done, ſince the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour was firſt ſo carefull to add in the ſame Letter the trouble he was in that he could no ſooner adviſe his Majeſty of what here paſſed, and how much his Majeſty was therein concerned that he might be well informed of what here paſſed, chiefly when therein may be remarked, that of himſelf and without order he dare not make the leaſt ſtep or advance though much thereto ſolicited, and how ſerviceable ſoever himſelf might judge it, how much he hath in regard the intereſt of his Maſter when he truly ſpeaketh; and agreed to points which might be urged of him yet with that precaution that his Majeſty ſhould not thereby be forepromiſed, than that his Maſter ſhould not thereby be too much engaged; and again that his Maſter might not be hindred to doe what he ſhould judge beſt? None can imagine that a Miniſter even in that Letter, who hath ſuch reſpect to his Maſter's intereſt, and with thoſe who ſeek to deal with him in that manner underſtandeth how to be able to Treat; and yet in the ſaid Letter to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the truth that happened otherwiſe than it came to paſs. It is alſo worth obſervation, that whereas the ſaid Lord Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour in the aforeſaid Memorial alledgeth, that for the ordering of a Conference concerning the Ship <hi>La Regle,</hi> he ſhould not have uſed the conduct, of which in the ſaid Letter mention is made: The Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> on the contrary by their advice acknowledge and avow that conduct. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It is to be obſerv'd that the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour by the foreſaid Memorial alledgeth, that the aforeſaid Letter either through ignorance or malice was wrong uncifered, and that therefore no credit was to be given to the ſame, whereas the mentioned Embaſſadour in that Memorial yieldeth that he had writ what had paſſed concerning the Ship <hi>La Regle</hi> ſo as it was uncifered; yea, that he had
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:95994:26"/>
written concerning the trouble of ſome of the Members of the State concerning the devaſtation of the open Countrey, by which the mentioned Barrier would come to ſink or vaniſh in the ſame manner as it is uncifered, from whence neceſſarily muſt follow that the ſame cifers which in the reſt were uſed alſo, ſignifie the ſame Letters which they have ſignified in the ſaid periods, and how can any one be taken for an Impoſtor or Cozener who ſendeth withall the Key wherewith he hath uncifered it, and who mentioneth the A. B. C. and the other Letter which by Cifers have been ſignified, which A. B. C. and thoſe other Letters have as well been uſed in the paſſages ſpoken of the foreſaid Ship <hi>La Regle,</hi> and the aforeſaid devaſtation of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid open Countrey, as in the other paſſages wherein is carped? he the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour toucheth further in the foreſaid Memorial on two paſſages, which he ſaith are very maliciouſly turned to a wrong ſenſe; the firſt is the paſſage which in what is uncifered inferreth, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> were but little moved concerning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended coming over of 135, for in the uncifering that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is uſed, and it is true that ſome Lords of the Government have thought that by that was meant the coming over of the Heer Penſionary <hi>Heinſius,</hi> ſince the ſame had as well writ from <hi>France</hi> as by word of mouth here reported that the State ought to put it ſelf in a poſture of Defence, then the Peace would then in all likelihood follow, and they muſt not ſuffer themſelves to be amuſed by promiſes to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect that which to the aforeſaid defence was neceſſary, and yet no man notwithſtanding hath ever ſaid, much leſs the unciferer of the aforeſaid Letter, that that number de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned the Heer <hi>Heinſius:</hi> what malignity there might be herein, I cannot conceive, for true it is, that the Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> would never give credit to that, nor to other advertiſements, thinking and always
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:95994:27"/>
ſaying they were better informed, and therein expreſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves even ſo far that in their turn giving their advice they feared not to ſay that although they were ſingular, yet it ſometimes happened that one alone might ſee as far and as much as all the reſt 18. But I pray what is there in this Explication that is ſo remarkably malicious, when the ſaid Embaſſadour ſaith, that the uncifering doth not infer that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> were not a little allarmed at the pretended arrival of that Letter, which ſaith that they onely ſought to abuſe them, when as no man that I know hath drawn out of that period any thing, or would charge on the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> as an offence, that they were more or leſs credulous or ſcrupulous. The Second period is that which ſpeaketh of the Heer <hi>Paets,</hi> and others well intentioned who had now again taken courage and joyned themſelves to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and who had ſaid to their friends that they never had conceived that his Majeſty would have done ſo much as was now done in <hi>Flanders</hi> with annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the number 180. It is true the words have but ſmall ſenſe, except onely that it might thereout be concluded, that the ſame whom the Lord Embaſſadour in that peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od named or deſigned began again to appear, encouraged thereto by the good which they never expected the King would have done or did. And the ſaid Embaſſadour ſaith not alone that that uncifering is falſe, but confirmeth the ſame very ſliff, when by the aforeſaid Memorial, he ſaith, that what is Cifered ſuppoſeth that all the well minded whom he there nameth good Republicans had reaſſumed courage, that they had ſaid to their friends that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had conceived that his Majeſty would doe ſo many things as he now did in favour of the good party, but that is true that no man hath thought that there was a party ſo affixed to <hi>France,</hi> and of which <hi>Amſterdam</hi> was the head, and for which his Majeſty would doe ſo many
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95994:27"/>
things, of which no man had given the Government any knowledge, either directly or indirectly; and thence had alſo been no knowledge thereof, if the ſaid Lord Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour had not ſo clearly mentioned it in the foreſaid Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, and had placed the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> and the good Republicans together; and in one place, what offence it is to make ſuch a Party in a State, and that alſo with Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, is very well known, and there be Capital Examples there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be produced out of the Regiſter of the States, which will alſo be ſhewn when the Matter ſhall be brought before the Judgment-ſeat. What concerneth the laſt Point con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſecurity, which ſhould be required of theſe of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in particular, I will ſpeak thereof no more, for that in my latter I have made ample mention thereof: I will onely ſay, that the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour hath ſaid by the ſaid Memorial, that he well knew particulars could not give it, and that his Majeſty never would have deſired it; and that yet the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in their Information ſay, That he the Lord Embaſſadour had often urged it from them, yea ſo far, that they denying it, he ſhould have expreſt his diſpleaſure; whether this agreeth together, judge ye. I can do no better than to ſay, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have ſuffered themſelves to be amuſed by deceitfull promiſes, as the Prieſt of the Lord Embaſſadour well ſaith in his Note, who by the ſaid Memorial they would ſay to be ſuch a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fellow, to thoſe who are not acquainted with him, but who hath a quite other reputation by thoſe to whom he is in any manner known. I will hencewith conclude, and onely ſay, that it needs muſt be a great grief to me and all good Patriots, that the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> have uſed ſo ill a Conduct, and taken ſo wrong a path, and to ſo great a diſadvantage of their Country, as to put and maintain the ſame in a State, without defence, through their abſtracting the ſaid Levy, and in that manner expoſe the ſame to the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:95994:28"/>
utmoſt danger on the Promiſe or Conditions of Peace, which by the State could not be brought forth, for that it depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the approbation of <hi>Spain,</hi> and which was declared by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters here, as alſo by the Miniſter of this State reſiding in <hi>Spain,</hi> that it never would be agreed to by <hi>Spain,</hi> let the event be what it will, and that they draw their deſign with ſo great immoderation and preſumption, that therein they neither would ſpare their Country nor the good Inhabitants thereof; and this obſtinateneſs is ſo much the more to be admired, for that it cannot be denied, but that of two matters, the one muſt be true; that is, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour by the foreſaid Letter doth repreſent the truth of what had paſſed between him and the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> in which Caſe the ſaid Lords of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> are notoriouſly guilty of Crimes, <hi>Laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> as is before demonſtrated, or that the aforeſaid Lord Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour hath not repreſented matters according to truth in the foreſaid Letter, and hath not therein proceeded with them in that juſt manner which ſo important a matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; in which Caſe the ſaid Lords of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> if they were ſuch good and ſincere Patriots as they pretend to be, and would clear themſelves of all Partiſhip, of which the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour maintaineth in the foreſaid Letter they ought to ſhew their Reſentment againſt thoſe who ſo wrongfully and inſinuatingly would make them to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; and finding themſelves amuſed by deceitfull promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and under colour thereof endeavoured to make the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhips, they would at laſt join with their fellow-members, and with ſuch zeal and inclination as was fitting, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to the eſtabliſhing of thoſe means which all their other fellow-members judge reaſonable and neceſſary for the common deſence without longer amuſing themſelves with thoſe who create ſuch intreagues to ſo great a detriment of the State, chiefly ſince the ſaid Lord Embaſſadour in his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:95994:28"/>
foreſaid Memorial is convinced, and clearly acknowledgeth that by the whole Government, how there is a great incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in a friendly manner to put a period to theſe differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by an Accommodation.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
